soft engineering radio episode 121
object relational mapper
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website possible
[Music]
hi everybody and welcome to another
episode of software engineering radio my
name is arnaud and today I am
interviewing me about object relational
mapper or our mappers the technology to
get object-oriented languages ensuing
for the database would you like to start
by introducing yourself saying a few
words about yourself okay
hi everybody thank you very much for
listening to this episode of se radio my
name is Michael flute I work for a
company called Sena core technologies in
Nuremberg Germany and my role is I'd say
chief developer Architect or however you
may call that role
usually working on longer running
projects and I started working with our
mappers a couple of years ago mainly
I've dealt with the Java based mappers
called like for instance hibernate or JD
or now nowadays jp8 the specification
and yeah I'm happy to hear some question
I hope I can answer them okay well let's
get started by talking about what is it
our mapper what is it about okay
basically a know our mapper is something
that addresses the object relational
mismatch there is a natural mismatch
between object-oriented software and
databases mainly if you if you look at
for instance how you group your business
logic or your domain object and how you
define a relational schema you will
clearly see from the beginning that for
instance you work with classes and
attributes and you have some sort of
types that are defined either by the
programming language or you define your
own types and in your in the programming
language you're working with on the
other hand you work with tables and
columns or and you you group these
things in schemas
and in a relational database you also
have a type system but this type system
is very static in most databases of
course a lot of databases have some sort
of user-defined types but usually this
support is not as sophisticated as the
support in a lot of the databases
another thing is the navigation how you
navigate between graphs of objects in
object-oriented software or in software
general you know how you navigate from
entity a to entity B on the other hand
the relational database the navigation
doesn't have a direction so you could
navigate from the customers table to the
billing details table without any
problems but you could also navigate
through the foreign key from the billing
details to the customers table so you
see there is no half of navigation okay
but but but to access this kind of data
you have the sequel programming language
or things like that why do you need an
or our mapper what is the advantage of
using an or our mapper arm above using
sequel and the the database access
technology of your language of choice to
directly access the database basically
you use a know our mapper to encapsulate
the database to certain degree a lot of
the vendors they say ok you can easily
switch the database by using a know our
mapper yes this is true but I would say
that in most of the big projects or big
companies out there switching a database
is a very very rare kind of thing I
think the major use case or the major
benefit of an hour I remember is to have
developers work with objects and not
have them code a lot of business logic
in statements or like the statement
processing that you mostly do with SQL
and in addition to that a lot of the
libraries that implement the
communication with SQL are very
low-level for instance if you look at
JDBC this is a very low-level library
where you work in statements you work
with result sets and you iterate over
them you have to do a lot of resource
management and a know our mapper totally
encapsulate cyou from this point of view
so you have some kind of metadata feed
for instance xml annotations or some
other kind of or even design of code
conventions that describe how you map
your classes to tables and how you map
relationships or inheritance or anything
else
so isn't or our mapper about making a
relational database look like in
object-oriented database now I don't
think
this is the the main intention of course
from a developer's point of view you
still work with objects and you have
some kind of access to the database like
for instance if you if you look at a JPA
or hibernate you have something like the
session or the entity manager which is a
persistence context which could be seen
as an oo database but they are no oo
database in the end or if you look at
active record where you were you call
some persistent related methods on your
object like say for a list or retrieve
or something like this I would say that
this is this is the wrong kind of thing
to look at and our mapper as treating it
as an oo database
they have some features of databases for
instance a lot of the queries from
certain or our mapper implementations
like with criterias and so on you also
find the stuff in our databases but in
the end the data gets persisted in a
relational storage so although you have
an object-oriented programming paradigm
you still should be aware that it is
stored in relational database because of
performance aspects and other non
functional aspects of your storage
absolutely I would say it's an illusion
to think that once you start using an
ORM / you don't have to bother about
relational concepts and SQL anymore I
know that there is a lot of advertising
regarding this issue but I think this is
actually very dangerous because you as a
developer that works with an overarm
ever have to be able to see what SQL is
being sent to the database and if this
is good SQL or bad SQL or if this is too
much SQL that gets sent to the database
so in my eyes if you start working with
a know our mapper
you still need to have some solid
background regarding SQL and the
relational database that you are using
especially when you do performance
tuning this is very important yeah I
understand that but a moment ago you
said you know our mapper encapsulate the
database and now you say you still need
to be aware of the SQL statements that
are passed between the or our mapper and
the database doesn't this reduce the
improvement you have doesn't this sort
of undermine the benefits of an hour I'm
ever yes and no there is some truth to
this because in the end our mapper is in
my eyes never a hundred percent solution
for every use case out there especially
when you want to do performance
improvements on leg on an integrated
legacy database I would say a know our
mapper is always a ninety five percent
solution or a ninety percent solution
regarding the problems that you face
when you integrate a relational database
to an object model I would say most of
the cases it is it is an a capsulation
so you don't write any statements
anymore you don't deal with low-level
resource management when you work with
an O our mapper and in most of the use
cases you just describe how an object
gets mapped to a database and you work
with it and you don't have any problems
of course there's corner cases where you
might think that falling back to SQL is
an option and I absolutely don't
discourage that option but just choose
it carefully only in absolute exceptions
falling back to SQL might be a solution
that is worth thinking about
okay so basically it's useful and takes
specially a lot of effort and have lit
up encapsulating for most of the cases
but in exceptional cases you still need
to be aware of things that go on below
that absolutely and so this is sort of
the label on beyond the PowerPoint and
an advertisement and buzzword level yes
it is useful but but you need to be
aware of the details in some cases
anyway of course I would say usually
when you roll out on or are mapper in a
team you have you need to have some
people in the team that have a detailed
knowledge of the o.r mapper and the SQL
and they spread the knowledge so that
the developer that is writing the
standard business logic in the team
doesn't need to care about all the bits
and the pieces I don't say that every
developer should should be an absolute
or our mapper or SQL Greg I can say that
you need to make sure that the knowledge
is available to you and it is also
absolutely fine for instance a Ruby or
Java developer to walk over to the DBA
and tell him listen
is that okay what I'm doing here I think
that there is often a lot of boundaries
between these teams and this is wrong
that there shouldn't be boundaries
between the teams that's certainly true
but let's get down more into the details
into the the the concepts behind the
facade of the or our mapper what doesn't
what I might actually do okay what I
know our mapper does is it takes some
sort of configuration in the beginning
for instance you define how you get to
the relational database if you are
working in a managed or non managed
environment for transactions
synchronizations and for looking up data
sources or connections to the database
there's some differences between with
the environments that you're running you
know but I don't want to get into detail
here because this is mostly
infrastructure related more important is
that an ORM mapper reads some kind of
metadata information where you specify
how you map objects to tables
how you define associations between the
objects and how these associations are
reflected in the database again there
are many options for instance you could
have a one-to-many relation over a join
table for instance because this relation
is optional and the database designer
didn't want to have nullable columns in
the database so you you need to specify
all of this and the o.r mapper takes
this information and is able to a
generate SQL that fits the operations
that you're doing on the or our mapper
to the database that you are running
under so another key concept of an or
our mapper is some kind of dialect so
the ORM ever needs to be able to talk to
as many databases as possible because
you want to abstract from a specific
database to many databases so this is
also the reason why our members are very
popular for
[Music]
software that is being sold that needs
to run in as many environments as
possible is a database different
database vendors solve the same problem
in different ways interpret the SQL
standard the different ways yes if you
are a pro knows how to how to speak the
dialects of a product without forcing
the developer to know all the details of
other products exactly absolutely and
the o.r mapper also has more knowledge
that recording SQL I would say a good
our mapper has that because some SQL on
some database is performing better than
some other SQL against the same database
so you would also have improved SQL in
the database dialect of the o.r mapper I
would say we get back to that point
later when we I think talk about
performance impacts of ORM FS yeah let's
do that
another thing key concept of an alarm
ever is the type system there are types
in the world of the programming language
that you are working with and also the
database has its own types so in some
cases you need to transform to these
types or the o.r mapper needs to have
facility how you map your own defined
types for instance currency amount where
you have an amount let's say 100 and you
have the currency US dollar how do you
store this object called currency amount
to the database so this is also a very
important part of the or metal the ORM
episode of adds abstraction you can work
as a high at a higher business sort of
abstraction when you persist your data
without being forced to do the
transformation explicitly all over the
place - raw sequel that what you are
talking about yes exactly
it's your abstract from a type system
like you have an you you as the Java
developer don't want to work or you as
the developer of software B Java or Ruby
or whatever want to work with your own
types and don't want to work with any o
our mapper or SQL specific types
and so the our mapper needs to abstract
from the underlying database types
that's what I meant
so we're saying an or our mapper
transforms the application type system
to the database type system and you
declare then the mapping between the
true in a single place so you can use
your application and business logic type
system over the place and directly map
it into the database exactly and in the
ideal case you have some defaults for
instance you map a string to a text or
of our character or something like this
in a database but you could also specify
okay I don't
I want to map this to that type okay
well what what about this was about
primitive types what about relations
between data references and foreign keys
and stuff yes this needs to be specified
in the metadata for the o.r mapper a
classical example regarding the
differences between a relational
database and object-oriented software
are m2m relationships in the relational
world you would work with three tables
for that you always have a mapping or a
join table in the middle that provides
you with the ability to define the end
to end relationship whereas in the
object-oriented software you would just
have two two classes with for instance
two collections on each of the sides so
you need to specify the relationships if
you want the relationship to be
unidirectional or be directional well
that's I would say in your code and then
you also need to specify how this
relation is
this relation is designed in the
database so for instance if you have a
one-to-many relationship and then you
specify - I have a join table for
instance if it's an optional
relationship or what is the foreign key
column and so on so this is a part of
the metadata and also of york wrote a
very important thing here is that most
in most of our members don't manage be
directional relationships for you so
this needs to be done in your code as
well what about object identity in the
relational world you have everything
value based and if two rows have the
same values in every column they're
indistinguishable there is in
programming languages and languages you
can have different objects that have
well the same values in all their fields
but still are two distinct objects how
do all our mappers bridge that gap yeah
if you define I would start off with
entities a lot of the other mappers
differentiate between components or
value objects for instance and entities
an entity always has a constant ID and
the object-oriented world this is a
concept for instance I was very nicely
explained by Eric evens in the
domain-driven design book and I like to
use these two kind of words for our
mappers as well let's start off with
entities an entity has a constant ID in
the relational world this refers to the
primary key of a table or of a column so
if the primary key is one of row of some
results at one and another rest of that
has the same primary key we're talking
about the same row this is the reason
why you would always specify a primary
key attribute or an ID attribute in an
ORM apper so there is a difference
usually you would work with one column
as the primary key and with one
attribute in your entity class but this
can also be extended to compose compose
primary keys where you have two or three
columns making up a primary key and you
would have two or three columns may two
or three attributes making up the
primary key or the ID of the object but
this is how the o.r mapper
reflects the primary key however there
is also the concept of object identity
for instance in Java you would implement
equals and hashcode for having a
business key and what I've seen is that
in a lot of projects the primary key
would be part of these methods which is
kind of dangerous because the primary
key might get created at a later stage
if you're working with the new objects
let's say you create a new customer and
the primary key would be created at the
end of the transaction or as soon as you
save the object to the database but so
you could have two customer objects one
with a set primary key by some default
mapping on the same service or web
service level and one that you just
instantiate it from a business point of
view you're talking about the same
object but if you have the primary key
in the equals and hashcode method you
would still get a difference between the
objects mm-hmm but how do the or our
mappers deal with the situation that you
can have several distinct objects in the
OL language that actually refer to the
same row in the database this this
concept of object identity which is not
present the database yes a very
important concept for some our mappers
there is the concept of object identity
this concept is found in any arm effort
that is working with some kind of
persistence context this is also called
the unit of word or and contains a
first-level caching system
and most of the other members that means
if I start a unit of work for instance I
have a easy a simple request and
response cycle on a web app I open the
persistence context and I load a
customer with the IDE one two three and
this customer is then being stored in
the persistence context if I go in
another business method to the
persistence concept and load the
customer with the same ID again I would
get the same object so also object a
equals equals object B would then return
true and so should of course equals and
hashcode if you close the persistence a
context or remove the object from the
persistence context you would no longer
have the guarantee of object identity so
in this case you can no longer trust
that you're still working with the same
object in this case okay basically you
have this you'd of work concept that we
corresponds to to the database
transaction and inside this unit of work
we have only one object corresponding
with the same row and then when you when
several transactions are running a
parallel memory and they couldn't commit
they'll have all kinds of conflicts but
this is the concept of our map is behind
it's armed
isolating several instances that refer
to the same row exactly yes this just
sounds like there are two things that
are our map is do one thing is reading
and modifying and primarily writing
objects yes and the other thing is
querying Assam reading data let's get to
the reading of data what support do or
our APIs have there I mean that's the
big strength of relational databases
that you have all the freedom in the
world to write arbitrary queries using
circle select
what do or our APIs do about that okay
um there are many ways to retrieve data
from a database through an or our mapper
usually they come with easy access
methods like query by a primary key
retrieve a proxy with an ID that gets
lazy initialized you could load all the
data from the database for instance what
you would find with find all methods for
instance in active record and then you
also have in most of our members a query
language and the big difference between
the query language of the Oh our mapper
and SQL is that in the case of a noir
mapper your query querying against
object and not against tables and
columns so this I would say if you if
you have a null sound SQL background and
you want to get into the query language
of a noir mapper the first thing you
have to be aware of is this difference
because you don't deal with tables and
another kind of query language is I
would say more object-oriented query
languages for instance with criteria
where you abstract from a text-based
query language to an object based query
language so you you have have an API for
just logging your queries together yes
you use an ape
and you define restrictions projections
you can defy ordering and you can also
specify how you want to fetch data from
the database because sometimes you know
that when you load for instance a
customer from a database you always want
to have his addresses all the addresses
that he or she the customer read
registered so you could do that in one
fetch so you can define fetching
strategies either in the object-oriented
querying with the API the criteria API
or you could do or you could also do
that in the text-based query language
another aspect is clearing by example
this is often part of the criteria api's
of the o.r mappers where you provide the
very instance with an example object for
instance any customer with the first
name or no and you would specify some
hints to the o.r mapper for instance a
match mode so that you say okay I want
an exact match I don't
I want to ignore the case and so on so
this is another querying facility that
especially comes in handy for search
screens and most of the other members
nowadays also have support for falling
back to a native SQL this is of course
not the the first choice you would do
when you work with a noir mepid but
there are use cases when you want to use
some database specific features or if
you want to do some very low-level
database tuning you could fall by back
to the native SQL and the o.r mapper
then provides you with an mapping from
the result set or from the low-level SQL
result that you get from the SQL query
to the object model that you are working
with
there used to be a hype of our mappers
the hype is sort of over but still a lot
of products call themselves our matters
there's all kinds of things there's
things like hibernate and hibernate
there's Ruby on Rails and the whole
group of products that sort of follow
that lead there is link there's all
kinds of things could you give us an
overview of what all kind of repairs
there are out there and what the
differences are maybe categorized them a
little okay I would start off with the
first categorization if an our mapper
has this concept of persistence context
or the unit of work or not in this range
there is for instance hibernate JDO was
also in this category or the in the java
world the JPA specification also
specifies a unit of work in this case
and hibernate is also part of this
category
the next category would be are members
that take metadata information but still
work very I would say statement oriented
for instance if you look at the support
in in Ruby on Rails you don't have the
persistence context in active record for
instance so you would create an object
save it to the database and if you then
change the object that you just saved to
the database you need to call an update
method so you don't get this transparent
synchronization with the database in
this case so here you always have to say
ok sync my changes with this object to
the database link on the other hand is
mainly a query language I mean link is
not just limited to a relational
database so you would have linked to
objects where you query objects in.net
you would have linked to xml where you
query on xml structures or linq to SQL
where you work with queries on a
database but also link
some kind of mapping between a very I
would say a very tool driven mapping for
mapping the the object to the tables in
the database but links main focus is
actually queries and they also have
means for storing and updating data in
the database but I would say the main
focus of link is querying there's also a
lot of discussion if for instance some
some low-level statement frameworks can
be seen as oh our mappers for instance
in the Java world you would have I betas
SQL maps so there you you also have some
kind of specification how you get from
objects to the database but this is very
statement oriented so I would see these
tools more or less in the framework
section and I wouldn't see them as our
members where they have some aspects of
our members but they are still very very
absolutely statement specific so you
define your own queries so these tools
they don't make up queries for your
objects they so you there there you have
to specify all they create read update
delete the crud operations and so on
yeah so that's the main categories I see
in terms of all our members
okay you sort of talked about the
different programming models of
different or our mappers um let's say I
want to start a new application and I am
thinking about I'm considering using an
or our mapper how do I go about it and
what impact does vor mapper have on the
design on the architecture of the new
application I'm writing okay
I would first evaluate if I really need
an O or mapper for my application if
this is a very small web app and you for
instance just have two or three classes
and you want to put them in the database
maybe an O our mapper would be just
another library more configuration more
metadata and you would have been very
much faster with plain SQL in this case
but most of the projects that that are
out there are more complex so in this
case I first want to need to evaluate
which kind of category of our mapper I
want to use do I want to have the
full-blown oh I remember
which is very powerful and in most cases
for the easy use case is also very easy
to use but they also add a complexity
because the developers in the team they
must be aware that for instance the
changes they make to objects get synced
to the database transparently for them
and you can also run into several areas
of conflict so it's their knowledge
about this kind of category for the o.r
mapper in the team this is the case you
can easily go ahead and integrate one of
these who are mappers to your team if
this is not the case maybe you add a
specialist for the ORM ever okay this is
sort of the the generic advice for
introducing new technology of any kind
but let's say I have a a business
application which is sufficiently large
and my preliminary research tells me
that hibernate and hibernate or one of
those well full-blown or our mappers is
a good
what impact does that have on the design
of the architecture of my application
how to worry about it okay
the impact is first of all that you you
have to add metadata to the application
so you usually then have your classes
and objects there are relationships
between them and you have the database
on the other hand and you have to put
them together for the oh I remember so
you need to specify metadata for that so
either through an external DSL or an
integrated configuration this is the
first thing another thing that you need
to integrate into your application is
the management of the persistence
context so the unit of work worth to my
units of work start how do I end them
how to sort of the the planning the
transaction borders exactly how do I
plan and integrate with the transaction
management am i working in a managed or
a non managed environment or do I need
to have support for long-running
conversations where I keep the
persistence context open but I commit
every time and flush manually at the end
and you also have to think what you do
with the mapped objects am i working
with am i passing them right through the
client application if I have one be the
web application or an RCP application or
am i working with another layer for the
service level for instance the DTO layer
so this also needs to be considered
okay let's say I'm starting the
development of a new application from
scratch which is sort of Li the best
case the dream of every developer do I
start by creating my object model and
then just map it to the database in
straightforward way or do a first design
my database and then sort of mirror the
database in the objects um how do I go
about that objects first or database
first there is
well usually when when you as a
object-oriented developer work with your
application you of course would say
object first and I would also think that
the objects that you're working with in
your application should be as
expressible as possible but I would
always maybe once a week talk to a
database specialist and say hey I have
this object structure and I want to make
map it like this to the database is that
fine or do you see any performance
impacts on this because if you if it has
a very if you have a very nice object
model but you
you screw it up on the database side the
the business value of the application
dramatically goes down I would always
start with the objects but keep the
persistence aspect in mind and think
critically and maybe have somebody
review how I think about the database as
well so basically you're saying objects
are the primary abstraction but it's
important to keep the database model in
mind and sort of do roundtrip and have
them both evolve in parallel yes I would
actually I would actually say this is
best
I would always work with sit down with a
domain expert who has a thorough domain
knowledge I would make up my object
model and then talk to a data designer
how he thinks or she thinks about this
object model and how we could reflect
that in the database what they think and
I think these collaborations between
these three views the the business side
the developers the oo developer side and
the database side will make up the most
efficient application okay another thing
is encapsulation of the ORM a per
product should I still have a data
access object layer
capsulate the or our member or should I
sort of use it all over the place
um I know there's some discussion about
this point especially in the context of
the Java persistence API specification
but I would still say absolutely yes for
the data access object pattern there are
several reasons for this a the first
reason is very obvious I don't want to
deal with persistent specific
technologies in my business logic this
is not part of the business logic and
the business logic shouldn't care about
where and how the data gets stored this
should be abstracted the next part is
you could switch the persistence
technologies and I would say this is the
weakest argument because usually you
evaluate a persistence technology you
tested your stress tested and then you
roll it out into a bigger development
environment and this is a very rare case
that you would switch a persistence
provider it happens I would say it
happens more often than you switch a
relational database but the main
advantage by having a Dao layer is that
you can define a standard behavior how
you for instance use the o.r mapas api
for instance do I always when I look up
stuff by the ID do I always hit the
database upfront or do I and generally
work with prot proxies do I for instance
in the case of hibernate use the method
save or update or do I want to work with
merge how do I flush the changes of the
persistence context to the database and
you're saying what you say what you're
saying is the the details of interacting
with the aura mapper API should be
abstracted away to be done in a uniform
way and not to clutter the business
logic that's that's one argument and the
other argument is that I can define
standardized crud behavior in an
abstract superclass of the AO that is
technology
specific and the developers in the ideal
case only need to implement queries okay
well what about lazy loading yes
well lazy loading is a feature that many
other mappers have and lazy loading
means that when you if you navigate
along object references and while you're
navigating along the object references
objects are pulled in in the background
sequel queries are executed in the
background doesn't this sort of behavior
sort of tie the business logic or create
a coupling of the business logic to the
persistence sort of through the backdoor
yes there is some kind of factor and you
I would say the lazy loading pattern is
a very good pattern because if we
wouldn't work with lazy loading in the
context of our members there would be a
danger that we would load up half of the
database on every request even if we
don't need the data so in the end the
lazy load pattern says ok I only need
really I'll only load stuff when I
really need it for instance if I load if
I have a collection and I need to access
some of the elements of the collection
the collection content gets lazily
loaded so in this case of course some
business logic triggers some SQL
statements but the business logic never
says ok now police persistence provider
initialize this for me it's happening
transparently in the business logic so I
I don't buy into the argument that there
is a tight coupling between persistence
and business logic through the lazy load
pattern being used but talking about
coupling and it impact what about the
overhead of having the or our mapper
stand in between your application in the
database doesn't that negatively affect
performance yes and no on the other on
the one side yes you have one additional
layer you have an additional library
that is running in the application and
this costs some performance I would say
it is with the majority of today's or
our mappers no longer a showstopper for
most applications maybe some extremely
high performance real time applications
they will consider this but a lot of the
enterprise applications that I've been
working on
they didn't even feel the overhead of
the aura mapper because on the other
side yo our mapper also
or let's say a good Oh our mapper sends
good SQL to the database regarding on
the dialect of the database that you are
working on so in the tie in the dialect
of a specific database there's also
knowledge how or which SQL is efficient
on that specific database and which SQL
is not space is not efficient so the
average developer that doesn't that has
usually some kind of knowledge of SQL
doesn't need to bother about the very
low level performance relevant details
of the database
this gets encapsulated and I've talked
to quite some DBS that say that the SQL
from many of our members is actually
pretty good for them there's not
everything is good about this but most
of the times they say in the end when
they test the use case the performance
is actually better
you mean the performance of accessing
the database through an or our mapper is
better then the performance would be for
with typical hand-coded sequel
statements
let's yes especially typical by an
average developer if you have developers
that a database experts and they can
they they will always be able to
outperform the or our mapper because
they know every bit and pieces but you
don't get the abstraction from the
database anymore and the applications
wouldn't be portable them sounds a
little like the discussion of the
performance impact of a virtual machine
versus hand-coded assembly language yep
something like this you will always find
people that say oh our members are so
slow but I think the reality is that not
every developer can be a database expert
in terms of writing the top performing
SQL for database X so
I think that I really think that Oh our
mappers at least don't drive down the
performance if you're using them right
mm-hmm well what about caching you said
that the unit of work usually does some
some caching too for for the abstraction
for the isolation between transactions
which is well it's sort of caching but
it's caching for the scope of a single
transaction
what about longer longer caching does it
pay to do that much level of support to
or our mappers have there is it good
idea to use that and if so when should
you use it and when truly avoid it okay
I'm I'm having a very conservative
stance on caching before I start
introducing second I second level
caching mechanism to know our mapper or
to the infrastructure of the Oh our
mapper my recommendation is to first
tune the plain data access so that means
only low data you really need think
about aggregation projection in queries
and tune the queries up front after this
has been done
I would assess which entities or which
use cases would benefit from caching
because not every kind of class would
benefit from caching for instance a very
bad candidate for a cash would be
financial data because if you run into a
problem with a cache your organization
could lose a lot of money on the other
hand reference data as for instance
country lists or
softer in my you mean master data data
that rarely changes and if you as
evidenced by me mad many other tables
yes I would I would classify this data
as data that rarely changes that is
being needed by many users and many many
different users and also data that gets
asked for a very often and data that is
not very critical I wouldn't want to
cache mission-critical data because
caching adds the risk of the cache being
outdated yes there you have to
differentiate between several isolation
levels for caches and most of the caches
or you can define a certain isolation
level this can be up to a fully
transactional cluster replicated cache
or to a simple cache that for instance
still maintains read committed isolation
on the transaction and that's working a
lot with idle times and that is not
shared across a cluster that is running
on one instance and not on many
instances and there is no
synchronization between the notes
so from this argumentation you also see
that you add some kind of complexity to
the infrastructure if you introduce a
cache this may not be very complicated
for smaller caches but if you want to
integrate a cache that is synchronized
across a cluster and fully transactional
and replicated and and so on you always
add a lot of complexity to the
infrastructure and this shouldn't be
done in my opinion by the specialist for
the o.r mapper in this case I would ask
a specialist for the cache because there
is a lot of stuff to configure there too
ok
so caching yes as sort of the last line
of defense but not something to to use
lightheartedly no I would say caching
yes but only introduced caching after
you have tuned everything else okay and
also query caches are widely used but
and most of the use cases they are not
very efficient in my eyes so you can
cache entities and relationships and
also queries for instance but a query
cache has a very rare justification I
would say no but still you can consider
this if you you know this query gets
executed with the same parameters up and
up again okay what about data migration
and all our mappers what about
applications accessing the database from
by different means then through the or
our mapper is that a problem absolutely
especially if you're working in an
environment with caching because your
application can never know when another
application changed the data in the
background this is mostly the use case
when you when you start off with an
existing database that has some so
procedures or other legacy applications
working on the database and then you set
up a new application with a new app
architecture where everything is nice
and great technologies and so on so then
you never have an occlusive access to
the database and you always need to be
aware that stuff can change in the in
the background and
[Music]
yes especially this is dangerous in a
caching environment in my eyes so in
this case I would be absolutely
conservative with caching and wouldn't
really recommend caching for most of the
entities you mentioned stored procedures
stored procedures are seen by many as
the fastest way to really
high-performance database applications
but stored procedures don't work very
well with our matters or do name
actually no you have support for store
procedures in our members but usually
the support is very limited and I
actually personally never integrated a
store procedure with an O our mapper of
course yes store procedures are
absolutely high-performing superfast and
so on but in the case of store
procedures you always have to be aware
that you bind like the data very
strongly with business logic of course
they are encapsulated in own packages
and so on but also the maintainability
of a store procedure is in my eyes
harder than the maintainability of
well-written
ohh-ohh code of course you could write
unmaintainable oo code but usually
especially when you want to find out for
instance oh where do I find that where
is that database link being used or
where do I use this and that this gets
very uncomfortable with store procedures
so sub procedures in my eyes are very
great for patching chops that's the
domain where most of the you are mappers
really fail because an or mapper is no
batching tool for high performance so
this is the Miis the main domain for the
store procedures well from my
perspective I think we basically covered
the ground other any final word you
would like to say anything you would
like to add yes thank you very much for
listening to the podcast I'd be happy to
take some feedback in the comments and
I'd be happy to reply to them regarding
using or our members I would definitely
encourage looking at all our members but
don't use them because they are fancy or
anything like that only add them when
there is a business value and especially
with caching be a little conservative
I'm not discouraging caching but just a
conservative stands to it and yeah don't
believe any ads that say you don't need
to learn SQL anymore this is a lie thank
you very much ok be here thank you very
much and thanks everybody to listening
by right
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to
solve the engineering radio soft
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website at st - radio
dot length if you want to support us you
can donate to the AC radio team via the
website or you can advertise for su
radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and slash dog
buttons to contact the team please send
email to team @ SC - radio net or if it
is specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of SU radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under
creative commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the pod safe music
Network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
travel
[Music]